A Guide to the Greensville County (Va.) Miscellaneous Records, 1781-1957
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Greensville County (Va.) Miscellaneous Records, 1781-1957
The Library of Virginia
1128761, 0007843094-0007843098, 0007843100-0007843104, 0007843124-0007843125, 0007843130, 0007843137
6.75 cu. ft. (15 boxes)
Greensville County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Miscellaneous Records, 1834-1870 that were transferred in accession 53810 under the title “Greensville County Dead Papers” and in adjacent boxes have undergone minimal processing. The remaining miscellaneous records from this locality are still unprocessed and need review prior to use by researchers. All records remain tri-folded or in original bundles and may be fragile. Contact Archives Research services for availability.
Acquisition Information
These records came to the Library of Virginia in a 2023 transfer of court papers from Greensville County under accession number 53810.
Historical Information
Context for Record Type: Powers of attorney were instruments conferring authority to act as attorney in fact of another person. These records are commonly related to land conveyances, and are often recorded in deed books.
Estrays were stray livestock found wandering. An inquest was held to determine the value of the livestock in order to reimburse the person who had found and cared for the animal. The report generally includes a physical description of the animal as well as an assessed monetary value.
Estray records give public notice of valuable, tame animals, either lost or found wandering and presumed escaped from their owners, allowing the owners to reclaim the animals. Entries generally indicate by whom the animal was taken up, before what justice the person went and when, and the description and appraisement (value) of the animal.
Locality History: Greensville County was named either for Revolutionary War general Nathanael Greene, commanding general of the Continental army in the South during part of the Revolutionary War, or for Sir Richard Grenville, leader of the Roanoke Island settlement of 1585. The county was formed from Brunswick County on 28 November 1780.
Scope and Content
Greensville County (Va.) Miscellaneous Records, 1781-1957, consist of records produced by a locality that do not fall easily into the main local record group categories. A portion of the miscellaneous records, 1834-1870, have undergone minimal processing. This has allowed for the documentation of specific record types and various trends found in this set of records. The remaining miscellaneous records are completely unprocessed.
Miscellaneous Records, 1834-1870 that have undergone minimal processing consist of the following:
Record Types:
Resolutions
Powers of attorney
Estray papers
Significant materials include county resolutions from 1864 thanking the Petersburg Rail Road Company for transporting Confederate soldiers free of charge during the Civil War.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Minimally Processed Miscellaneous Records, 1834-1870, are loosely arranged chronologically.
Series II: Unprocessed Miscellaneous Records, 1781-1957, are housed in boxes with other unprocessed court records for Greensville County.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also Greensville County (Va.) Ministers' Returns and Certificates of Strays, 1781-1851 at the Library of Virginia.
Additional Greensville County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm."
Contents List
- Minimally Processed Miscellaneous Records, 1834-1870, .45 cubic feet (1 box)
  Loosely arranged chronologically.
  - Bonds/Commissions/Oaths; Clerk; Commissioner of Revenue; Election; Fiduciary; Health and Medical; Jury; Justice of the Peace; Miscellaneous; Military and Pension; Overseers of the Poor; Property; Public Buildings; School; Sheriff; Treasurer; Wills, 1792-1870
- Unprocessed Miscellaneous Records, 1781-1957, 6.3 cubic feet (14 boxes)
  Housed in boxes with other unprocessed court records for Greensville County.
  - Ministers' Returns and Certificates of Strays, 1781-1851 (bulk 1785-1851)
  - Criminal; Miscellaneous Papers, 1872-1877
  - Criminal; Miscellaneous Papers, 1878-1884
  - Court Papers; Miscellaneous Papers, 1884-1887
  - Court Papers; Miscellaneous Papers, 1887-1889
  - Court Papers; Criminal; Miscellaneous Papers, 1890-1891
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1894-1896
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1897-1899
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1898-1901
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1901-1903
  - Miscellaneous Papers; Wills, 1903-1931; 1927-1959
  - Apprentice' Indentures; Ministers' Bonds; Lists of Licenses; Guardian's; Administrators'; Public Officers'; Miscellaneous Papers, 1788-1870
  - Apprentice' Indentures; Ministers' Bonds; Lists of Licenses; Guardian's; Liquor; Bar Room Keepers'; Administrators'; Public Officers'; Miscellaneous Papers, 1872-1890
  - Escrow; Deeds Not Properly Proven; Miscellaneous Records, 1874-1957